Dr. Gráinne Costigan -

Working in the most competitive and notable research institutes in Europe has given me strong team working skills, with a focus on attaining the end goal using innovative techniques and tools. I am currently working as a statistical data scientist within the global supply chain forecasting group at Sanofi.

EXPERIENCE -

Statistical Data Scientist

Sanofi, Barcelona Dec. 2020 - Today Statistical Data Scientist within the global supply chain forecasting team for Sanofi products.

Senior Data Scientist

HP Inc, Barcelona April 2018 - Nov 2020 Technical lead for a diverse set of projects across the bussiness (production & commercial printers) working with local and remote coworkers (India, US, Singapore, China).

- Projects include smart servicing of printer fleets, anomaly detection, customer segmentation and COVID impact assesments. (contact for more details)
- · Working with telemetry data from printers as well as customer service reports and business generated data sets.
- · Mentoring of new graduates within team.
- · Promotion of data driven culture within HP Barcelona, leading active learning and sharing of data science methods across the business.
- · Presentation of work at AI & Big Data congress 2019

Main technologies: AWS, SQL, python, Jira, powerBI Skills: Project management, business use case identification, data wrangling, bayesian methods, neural network interpretation.

Data Science Fellow

S2DS with Pivigo, London Aug. 2017 – Sept 2017 As intern with SNTV, a world leading sports news video content provider, I was working on a 5 weeks, time boxed, data project to do a detailed customer segmentation and associated assessment of resource allocation.

- · Part of a team of 3 which carried out first in-depth data analysis of content broadcast and download data.
- · Performed customer segmentation in order to deepen understanding of how SNTV's content is used and identify undervalued and/or ineffective content.
- Provided further understanding of change in market due to rise in digital media and how this affects SNTV clients.
- Building of recommendation system to provide individual recommendations for SNTV clients.

Main Technologies: Python (scikit learn) Skills: Customer Segmentation. Identifying Market Trends. Statistical Analysis. Clustering. Recommender Systems.

Travel & Personal Development

May 2016 - Aug 2017

During this period I traveled through latin america learning Spanish and volunteering.

Research Associate

Leiden University May 2014 – May 2016 Participated in the development of 'Big Data' (1 PB) scientific data archive – latest european astronomical all sky survey.

- Took a lead role in beta testing of archive: co-organised a team of 10 scientific testers, gathered amateur astronomer testers, collated all test cases and implemented and tested these in SQL. I then raised issues and liaised with the European Space Agency (ESA) archive development team to identify areas of weakness within the archive access software.
- · Worked alongside ESA and private companies to develop archive tools: established companies had access to necessary data, understood archive contents and limitations of data (while limited data sets available).
- · Wrote the long term data preservation plan, contributed to testing of data traceability and to the collection and validation of data.
- Designed and supervised multiple student projects, Msc and PhD level taking place over time periods of 3-6 months.

Junior Researcher

ESO, Munich DIAS, Dublin Oct. 2009 – Nov. 2013

EXPERIENCE

Based between four different research institutes while working towards my PhD in astronomy, I developed effective communication skills, an independent work ethic and good project development skills.

- · Performed rigorous testing for biases within data, cleaning methods and analysis.
- · Learnt to work as an effective team member locally and remotely.
- · Awarded three research grants together worth over € 100,000.

Main Technologies: MIDAS (FORTRAN based). IDL.

Skills: Time Series Analysis. Data Visualisation and Communication. Data Cleaning.

Junior Researcher

Space Lab, Dundee University, Scotland Oct. 2008 – Oct. 2009 Implementing and testing of computer vision algorithms for planetary rover navigation.

Main Technologies: MATLAB/Octave.

Skills: Algorithm implementation and development.

EDUCATION

PhD Dec. 2014

Graduated Queen's University Belfast (Northern Ireland)

Masters 2007 – 2008

Cambridge University (UK), Master of Mathematics. CASM Part III

Bachelors 2003 – 2007

Trinity College Dublin (Ireland), Theoretical Physics, BA (mod)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

+ [beginner] ++ [intermediate] +++ [expert]

Python. +++
R. +
SQL. ++
BASH. +++
Unix/Linux. +++
MATLAB/Octave. ++
MIDAS (FORTRAN based). ++
IDL. ++
Git. ++
Jira. ++

AWS (EC2, Lambda, S3). +

Jan - March 2020

Barcelona.

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

Inspira Mentor – Leading six sessions with 10/11 year olds exploring the influence of gender in STEAM careers. [Done through spanish]

Spring 2019

Barcelona.

Hour of code volunteer - teaching 10 year olds through hour long sessions how to begin coding. [Done through spanish]

Feb. 2017 – Jan. 2018 DataKind, Dublin. DataKind is a group of data science volunteers working together to help not-forprofit organisations. Part of the work is to demonstrate and educate the NGOs on the power of data science and what it can be learnt from it.

Skills: NPL. Google Analytics. Modeling Intervention Effectiveness. Decision Trees.

Sept. 2016

Bogotá, Colombia.

Science teaching in a primary school as part of a three week voluntary placement. Designed and implemented program for all classes which involved 150 kids.

Languages •

English (native).

Spanish (certified B2.4 – use it daily in professional & social envirnoments)

Personal Interests

Kite surfing, Crossfit, Food, Traveling, Teaching and Learning new things.